"Can Getting Transfusions of
Young Blood Slow Aging?"
Vampires 2.0?
The ethical quandaries
of young blood infusion
in the quest for eternal life.
In an episode of the TV series
Silicon Valley entitled,
"The Blood Boy,"
a tech guru hires
a young assistant
from whom to transfuse
pints of blood
in an attempt to slow down
his aging.
The restoration of youth
by bathing in or drinking
the blood of youth
is a centuries-old trope
dating back at least
to the futile attempt
of ailing Pope Innocent VIII,
who, in the 1490s,
failed to live up to his name
by apparently drinking the blood
of three ten-year-old boys,
who, though a bargain--
"costing only
one ducat apiece"--
died in the process.
Might there be something
to it, though?
Though young blood did
not have a significant impact
on lifespan, otherwise,
infusing the blood
of young animals into old
did have a rejuvenating effects
on multiple organs
similar to
full-blown parabiosis,
as I talked about
in the last video.
In fact, not only does the
infusion of young mouse blood
improve age-related cognitive
dysfunction in old mice,
young human blood,
taken from umbilical cords,
worked too,
in mice engineered to not reject
the foreign tissue.
This led
to ongoing clinical trials
offering weekly infusions
of blood products
from young donors
to patients
with mild to moderate
Alzheimer's disease.
But there may be
an easier way.
Yes, the injection of blood
from young mice into old
can improve memory
and learning,
suggesting there's some kind
of restorative youth factor,
but the injection of blood
from old mice into young
can worsen memory and learning,
suggesting that instead
there's some sort
of debilitating aging factor.
Or maybe the old blood
is just diluting
the revitalizing factor
in the young mouse,
or, for that matter,
maybe the young blood
is diluting
the debilitating factor
in the old mouse.
The fact that old blood
appears to make things worse
more than young blood
makes them better
suggests maybe the latter
is the case,
but you don't know,
until you put it to the test.
Ready for a mind-blowing shift
in perspective?
Instead of infusing young blood
into old mice,
researchers at UC Berkeley
just diluted
the blood of old mice
by siphoning off the plasma,
the liquid portion of the blood,
and essentially replacing
half of it with water.
If the regeneration seen
in heterochronic parabiosis
and blood transfusions
were due to some
fountain of youth factor
in young blood,
then nothing should happen,
right?
But if all the young blood
was doing
was diluting
some debilitating aging factor,
then the water should work
just as well,
and it did.
The rejuvenation in the liver
was similar to parabiosis
or transfusion,
and in the muscles and the brain
it was even better.
So, most if not all the benefits
could be replicated
by simple dilution,
including an improvement
in cognitive capacity.
That's good news,
since there's already
an FDA approved procedure
in use today known
as therapeutic plasma exchange.
It's usually used to filter out
toxins or autoimmune antibodies,
but why not try using it
to try to dilute old blood
to treat Alzheimer's disease?
And that's exactly what
researchers did.
Hundreds of Alzheimer's patients
were randomized to a therapeutic
plasma exchange procedure,
or a placebo (sham) procedure,
and though it didn't seem
to help those
with mild Alzheimer's disease,
those with moderate Alzheimer's
randomized to the real procedure
experienced about 60% less
cognitive and functional decline
over a period of 14 months.
This is in stark contrast
to mainstay treatments
for Alzheimer's
like the drug memantine
that can help with symptoms
but don't actually change
or alter
the course of the disease.
And the added advantage
over blood transfusions,
as a Director of an Institute
of Biomedical Ethics put it:
"There is something peculiar
about the old literally
feeding on the young."